## ANTONY HOLMES

Data scientist and full stack software developer with 8 years experience developing open source software and applications for cancer genetics research. Experienced in the full software development life-cycle from requirement definition, prototyping, design, interface implementation, and maintenance. Excellent written and oral communication skills demonstrated by more than 24 publications and teaching courses on Unix/Linux and bioinformatics to graduate students.

### CONTACT

**347) 688-5690** 

github.com/antonybholmes

in linkedin.com/in/antonybholmes

### **EDUCATION**

PH.D MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY

2009, University of Warwick UK

SIWN Best Paper Award

M.SC COMPUTER SCIENCE

2004, University of Warwick UK

**B.SC COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

2003, University of Warwick UK

First-class honours

### Experience

#### 2015-present SENIOR BIOINFORMATICS DEVELOPER

Columbia University

Full stack systems engineer with expertize developing web based genomics tools and databases using Java, Python, and Javascript.

Migrated lab data and core applications onto AWS cloud infrastructure using a mixture EC2, S3, and RDS services reducing costs by 90%.

Created a new Institute for Cancer Genetics department web site within a budgeted 6 month timeframe using a static site single page application written in **React+JSX** to implement modern web standards, ease deployment and updates, and reduce costs by 80%.

Developed multi-user database genomic web applications running on AWS using Django, API Gateway, and Postgresql to allow users remote access to core lab data and analysis to improve productivity.

### 2012-2015 ASSOCIATE RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Columbia University

Developed expertise in analyzing microarray, SNP 6.0, RNA-seq, Chip-seq, and single cell genomic data using next generation sequencing tools.

Developed cluster based data pipelines using **Python**, **R**, and **BASH** to run next generation sequencing and big data analysis that reduced analysis time from days to hours.

Core **Java** developer creating desktop applications empower scientists to analyse data on their own. The applications are available as an open source suite of specialized genomics tools on GitHub.

Published over **20** articles on B-cell development and genetic lesions associated with development in high impact journals, including Nature, Cell, Blood, and the New England Journal of Medicine.

#### 2009-2012 POST DOCTORAL RESEARCH SCIENTIST

Columbia University

Data mining electronic health records (EHR) at New York Presbyterian Hospital.

Onboarded as database administrator to create a research version of the hospital EHR system for multi-user access to researchers.

Studied patterns of influenza to look for predictive power in hospital records for New York public health.

Discovered novel relationships between rare diseases and comorbidities which were developed into **MATLAB** and **Java** applications to offer potential avenues for new therapeutics. This work resulted in three publications.

### Volunteer Work

2015-present TAX TEAM LEADER

New York Cares

IRS certified tax preparer helping New Yorkers file their tax

returns for free during tax season.

Work with clients one-on-one to understand their tax situation

and prepare their federal and state returns.

Save clients \$30,000 in fees per year.

Manage a small team of volunteers and act as a liaison between

New York Cares and partner organizations.

Quality review tax returns for accuracy before filing.

### Skills

Programming Languages

Java

Python

Pandas, Numpy, Scikit-learn,

Spring Boot, Maven

Django Databases

Web

Node, React, Electron, Gatsby, JSX, TypeScript, HTML/CSS

Swing, JavaFX, Apache-Math,

PostgreSQL, MySQL, Sqlite

Math R. MATLAB

Software

AWS

EC2, S3, Lambda, CloudFront,

**API** Gateway

Development

Eclipse, Visual Studio Code, Git

Cluster

SGE, BSUB

Office

Microsoft Office, LaTeX,

Inkscape, Photoshop, Illustrator

Bioinformatics

Development

Sequencing

Bowtie, Hisat2, STAR, ChIPseeqer, 10x Cell Ranger **Tools** 

GSEA, GenePattern, BLAST

Source code for this resume is available at: github.com/antonybholmes/resume

### References

Prof. Riccardo Dalla-Favera

Institute for Cancer Genetics Columbia University New York

rd10@columbia.edu

Prof. Katia Basso

Institute for Cancer Genetics Columbia University

New York

kb451@cumc.columbia.edu

### Prof. Raul Rabandan

Department of Systems Biology Columbia University New York

rr2579@cumc.columbia.edu

### **Publications**

#### 1. Single-cell analysis of germinal-center B cells informs on lymphoma cell of origin and outcome

Holmes AB, Corinaldesi C, Shen Q, Kumar R, Compagno N, Wang Z, Nitzan M, Grunstein E, Pasqualucci L, Dalla-Favera R, Basso K

J Exp Med. 2020.

### 2. miR-939 acts as tumor suppressor by modulating JUNB transcriptional activity in pediatric anaplastic large cell lymphoma

Garbin A, Lovisa F, Holmes AB, Damanti CC, Gallingani I, Carraro E, Accordi B, Veltri G, Pizzi M, d'Amore ESG, Pillon M, Biffi A, Basso K, Mussolin L

Haematologica. 2020.

## 3. Unique and Shared Epigenetic Programs of the CREBBP and EP300 Acetyltransferases in Germinal Center B Cells Reveal Targetable Dependencies in Lymphoma

Meyer SN, Scuoppo C, Vlasevska S, Bal E, Holmes AB, Holloman M, Garcia-Ibanez L, Nataraj S, Duval R, Vantrimpont T, Basso K, Brooks N, Dalla-Favera R, Pasqualucci L

Immunity. 2019.

### 4. MEF2B Instructs Germinal Center Development and Acts as an Oncogene in B Cell Lymphomagenesis

Brescia P, Schneider C, Holmes AB, Shen Q, Hussein S, Pasqualucci L, Basso K, Dalla-Favera R Cancer Cell. 2018.

### 5. Common nonmutational NOTCH1 activation in chronic lymphocytic leukemia

Fabbri G, Holmes AB, Viganotti M, Scuoppo C, Belver L, Herranz D, Yan XJ, Kieso Y, Rossi D, Gaidano G, Chiorazzi N, Ferrando AA, Dalla-Favera R

Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017.

### 6. The CREBBP Acetyltransferase Is a Haploinsufficient Tumor Suppressor in B-cell Lymphoma

Zhang J, Vlasevska S, Wells VA, Nataraj S, Holmes AB, Duval R, Meyer SN, Mo T, Basso K, Brindle PK, Hussein S, Dalla-Favera R, Pasqualucci L

Cancer Discov. 2017.

#### 7. The genetics of nodal marginal zone lymphoma

Spina V, Khiabanian H, Messina M, Monti S, Cascione L, Bruscaggin A, Spaccarotella E, Holmes AB, Arcaini L, Lucioni M, Tabbò F, Zairis S, Diop F, Cerri M, Chiaretti S, Marasca R, Ponzoni M, Deaglio S, Ramponi A, Tiacci E, Pasqualucci L, Paulli M, Falini B, Inghirami G, Bertoni F, Foà R, Rabadan R, Gaidano G, Rossi D Blood. 2016.

## 8. Prognostic and therapeutic role of targetable lesions in B-lineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia without recurrent fusion genes

Messina M, Chiaretti S, Wang J, Fedullo AL, Peragine N, Gianfelici V, Piciocchi A, Brugnoletti F, Di Giacomo F, Pauselli S, Holmes AB, Puzzolo MC, Ceglie G, Apicella V, Mancini M, Te Kronnie G, Testi AM, Vitale A, Vignetti M, Guarini A, Rabadan R, Foà R Oncotarget. 2016.

### 9. The FOXO1 Transcription Factor Instructs the Germinal Center Dark Zone Program

Dominguez-Sola D, Kung J, Holmes AB, Wells VA, Mo T, Basso K, Dalla-Favera R Immunity. 2015.

### 10. Genomic and proteomic characterization of two novel siphovirus infecting the sedentary facultative epibiont cyanobacterium Acaryochloris marina

Chan YW, Millard AD, Wheatley PJ, Holmes AB, Mohr R, Whitworth AL, Mann NH, Larkum AW, Hess WR, Scanlan DJ, Clokie MR Environ Microbiol. 2015.

### 11. Disruption of KMT2D perturbs germinal center B cell development and promotes lymphomagenesis

Zhang J, Dominguez-Sola D, Hussein S, Lee JE, Holmes AB, Bansal M, Vlasevska S, Mo T, Tang H, Basso K, Ge K, Dalla-Favera R, Pasqualucci L

Nat Med. 2015.

### 12. MicroRNA 28 controls cell proliferation and is down-regulated in B-cell lymphomas

Schneider C, Setty M, Holmes AB, Maute RL, Leslie CS, Mussolin L, Rosolen A, Dalla-Favera R, Basso K Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014.

### 13. Genetic lesions associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia chemo-refractoriness

Messina M, Del Giudice I, Khiabanian H, Rossi D, Chiaretti S, Rasi S, Spina V, Holmes AB, Marinelli M, Fabbri G, Piciocchi A, Mauro FR, Guarini A, Gaidano G, Dalla-Favera R, Pasqualucci L, Rabadan R, Foà R Blood. 2014.

### 14. Genetics of follicular lymphoma transformation

Pasqualucci L, Khiabanian H, Fangazio M, Vasishtha M, Messina M, Holmes AB, Ouillette P, Trifonov V, Rossi D, Tabbò F, Ponzoni M, Chadburn A, Murty VV, Bhagat G, Gaidano G, Inghirami G, Malek SN, Rabadan R, Dalla-Favera R Cell Rep. 2014.

### 15. Genetic lesions associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia transformation to Richter syndrome

Fabbri G, Khiabanian H, Holmes AB, Wang J, Messina M, Mullighan CG, Pasqualucci L, Rabadan R, Dalla-Favera R J Exp Med. 2013.

## 16. tRNA-derived microRNA modulates proliferation and the DNA damage response and is down-regulated in B cell lymphoma

Maute RL, Schneider C, Sumazin P, Holmes A, Califano A, Basso K, Dalla-Favera R Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013.

### 17. BCL6 positively regulates AID and germinal center gene expression via repression of miR-155

Basso K, Schneider C, Shen Q, Holmes AB, Setty M, Leslie C, Dalla-Favera R J Exp Med. 2012.

## **18.** Identification of human germinal center light and dark zone cells and their relationship to human B-cell lymphomas Victora GD, Dominguez-Sola D, Holmes AB, Deroubaix S, Dalla-Favera R, Nussenzweig MC

Blood. 2012.

## 19. The coding genome of splenic marginal zone lymphoma: activation of NOTCH2 and other pathways regulating marginal zone development

Rossi D, Trifonov V, Fangazio M, Bruscaggin A, Rasi S, Spina V, Monti S, Vaisitti T, Arruga F, Famà R, Ciardullo C, Greco M, Cresta S, Piranda D, Holmes A, Fabbri G, Messina M, Rinaldi A, Wang J, Agostinelli C, Piccaluga PP, Lucioni M, Tabbò F, Serra R, Franceschetti S, Deambrogi C, Daniele G, Gattei V, Marasca R, Facchetti F, Arcaini L, Inghirami G, Bertoni F, Pileri SA, Deaglio S, Foà R, Dalla-Favera R, Pasqualucci L, Rabadan R, Gaidano G J Exp Med. 2012.

## 20. Combined genetic inactivation of $\beta$ 2-Microglobulin and CD58 reveals frequent escape from immune recognition in diffuse large B cell lymphoma

Challa-Malladi M, Lieu YK, Califano O, Holmes AB, Bhagat G, Murty VV, Dominguez-Sola D, Pasqualucci L, Dalla-Favera R Cancer Cell. 2011.

# **21.** Whole-exome sequencing identifies somatic mutations of BCOR in acute myeloid leukemia with normal karyotype Grossmann V, Tiacci E, Holmes AB, Kohlmann A, Martelli MP, Kern W, Spanhol-Rosseto A, Klein HU, Dugas M, Schindela S,

Trifonov V, Schnittger S, Haferlach C, Bassan R, Wells VA, Spinelli O, Chan J, Rossi R, Baldoni S, De Carolis L, Goetze K, Serve H, Peceny R, Kreuzer KA, Oruzio D, Specchia G, Di Raimondo F, Fabbiano F, Sborgia M, Liso A, Farinelli L, Rambaldi A, Pasqualucci L, Rabadan R, Haferlach T, Falini B Blood. 2011.

### 22. Discovery of cyanophage genomes which contain mitochondrial DNA polymerase

Chan YW, Mohr R, Millard AD, Holmes AB, Larkum AW, Whitworth AL, Mann NH, Scanlan DJ, Hess WR, Clokie MR Mol Biol Evol. 2011.

### 23. BRAF mutations in hairy-cell leukemia

Tiacci E, Trifonov V, Schiavoni G, Holmes A, Kern W, Martelli MP, Pucciarini A, Bigerna B, Pacini R, Wells VA, Sportoletti P, Pettirossi V, Mannucci R, Elliott O, Liso A, Ambrosetti A, Pulsoni A, Forconi F, Trentin L, Semenzato G, Inghirami G, Capponi M, Di Raimondo F, Patti C, Arcaini L, Musto P, Pileri S, Haferlach C, Schnittger S, Pizzolo G, Foà R, Farinelli L, Haferlach T, Pasqualucci L, Rabadan R, Falini B

N Engl J Med. 2011.

### 24. Discovering disease associations by integrating electronic clinical data and medical literature

Holmes AB, Hawson A, Liu F, Friedman C, Khiabanian H, Rabadan R PLoS One. 2011.

### 26. Signs of the 2009 influenza pandemic in the New York-Presbyterian Hospital electronic health records

Khiabanian H, Holmes AB, Kelly BJ, Gururaj M, Hripcsak G, Rabadan R PLoS One. 2010.

### 27. Spatial simulations of myxobacterial development

Holmes AB, Kalvala S, Whitworth DE PLoS Comput Biol. 2010.

# 28. Phosphate acquisition components of the Myxococcus xanthus Pho regulon are regulated by both phosphate availability and development

Whitworth DE, Holmes AB, Irvine AG, Hodgson DA, Scanlan DJ J Bacteriol. 2008.